A Guide to the Records of the Principal and Assistant Assessors, 1817-1838
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of Principal and Assistant Assessors, 1817-1838
The Library of Virginia
50577
2.7 cubic feet
Virginia. Governor's Office.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition information unknown
Biographical Information
An act was passed by the General Assembly on 18 February 1817 entitled an act arranging the counties into districts for the election of senators and for equalizing the land tax. A similar act was passed on 24 March 1838 providing for the reassessment of lands in the Commonwealth. These acts established a board of principal assessors of four members for the newly created four districts. These acts also called for the appointment of assistant assessors in every county appointed by the Executive and recommended by the county court.
Scope and Content
The Records of the Principal & Assistant Assessors are arranged into two series. Series have been designated for Principal & Assistant Assessors. These records document the recommendation, application, and sometimes commission of the principal & assistant assessors of the land tax in 1817 and 1838.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Principal Assessors
Subseries 1: 1817
Subseries 2: 1838
Series II: Assistant Assessors
Subseries 1: 1817
Subseries 2: 1838
Contents List
- Series I: Principal Assessors, 1817-1838., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  This series is organized into two subseries with subseries related to the Act of 1817 and the other series the Act of 1838.
  Arranged in two subseries.
  - Subseries 1: 1817
    Subseries 1 contains correspondence to Gov. James P. Preston and members of the Council of State from individuals applying for the position of principal assessor in 1817.
    Arranged alphabetically by locality.
    - Accomack-Augusta (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bath-Botetourt (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Campbell-Culpeper (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dinwiddie-Greensville (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Halifax-Henry (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Isle of Wight-Montgomery (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Northumberland-Wythe (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: 1838
    Subseries 2 is arranged by district, then alphabetically by locality. This subseries contains lists of individuals recommended as principal assessors. There is also correspondence to Gov. David Campbell recommending individuals as principal assessors.
    - District 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - District 2
      - Accomack-Henrico (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Loudoun-Prince William (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - District 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - District 4 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II: Assistant Assessors, 1817-1838., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 3-6)
  This series is organized into two subseries with subseries related to the Act of 1817 and the other subseries related to the Act of 1838.
  - Subseries 1: 1817
    Subseries 1 is divided into two types of correspondence: one type relates to completed assessments and the other relates to recommendations of assistant assessors. The correspondence regarding completed assessments consists of letters from assistant assessors from various localities to Gov. James P. Preston notifying him of the completion of the reassessment of lands & lots in the Commonwealth. The other type of correspondence relates to county court recommendations & court orders for assistant assessors. The correspondence is addressed to Gov. James P. Preston and sometimes includes commissions from the governor.
    - Completed Assessments
      - Accomack-Cumberland (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Dinwiddie-Isle of Wight (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - James City-Montgomery (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Nansemond-Princess Anne (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Richmond-York (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Recommendations, etc.
      - Accomack-Cumberland (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Dinwiddie-Henry (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Isle of Wight-Monroe (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Nansemond-Princess Anne (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Randolph-York (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: 1838
    Subseries 2 contains court orders for the recommendation of assistant assessors, polls, petitions, and letters of recommendation addressed to Gov. David Campbell.
    - Accomack-Buckingham (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Cabell-Essex (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Fairfax-Greensville (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Halifax-Jefferson (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Kanawha-Lunenburg (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Madison-Nottoway (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ohio-Preston (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Prince Edward-Sussex (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Tazewell-York (Box 6, Folder 3)